<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://maxzimmer.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://maxzimmer.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2026-02-21T12:12:02+00:00</updated><id>https://maxzimmer.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Academic website of Max Zimmer. Deep Learning Research Lead at the IOL Lab of ZIB. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Approximating Latent Manifolds in Neural Networks via Vanishing Ideals</title><link href="https://maxzimmer.org/blog/2025/approximating-latent-manifolds-in-neural-networks/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Approximating Latent Manifolds in Neural Networks via Vanishing Ideals"/><published>2025-05-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-05-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://maxzimmer.org/blog/2025/approximating-latent-manifolds-in-neural-networks</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://maxzimmer.org/blog/2025/approximating-latent-manifolds-in-neural-networks/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="the-manifold-hypothesis">The Manifold Hypothesis</h2> <p>A foundational concept in understanding the efficacy of deep neural networks is the <em>Manifold Hypothesis</em> <d-cite key="fefferman2013testing"></d-cite>. This hypothesis posits that real-world, high-dimensional data (such as images or text) does not uniformly occupy the vastness of the space it lives in. Instead, it tends to concentrate on or near lower-dimensional <em>manifolds</em>. For example, while an image might be represented by thousands of pixel values, the set of images depicting a particular object class (e.g., “cats”) might form a manifold with a much smaller inherent dimensionality, accounting for variations like pose, lighting, and individual appearance.</p> <p>Neural networks are often conceptualized as learning complex functions that progressively transform these input data manifolds. Through successive layers, a network can reshape and disentangle these manifolds, ideally leading to representations in its <em>latent spaces</em> where the data becomes more structured or even linearly separable for tasks like classification <d-cite key="brahma_why_2016"></d-cite>. For instance, the initially intertwined manifolds of “cat” and “dog” images might be transformed such that, in a deeper layer, they occupy distinct, more easily distinguishable regions of the latent space.</p> <p>To characterize these latent manifolds, we seek to find their algebraic descriptions. Fortunately, many manifolds encountered in such settings can be described as the zero set of a system of polynomial equations. Such a system formally defines an <em>algebraic variety</em>. For example, a sphere in three-dimensional Euclidean space, representing a simple manifold, is defined by all points $(x, y, z)$ that satisfy the single polynomial equation $x^2 + y^2 + z^2 - r^2 = 0$. This algebraic perspective is central to our work, which pursues two primary objectives. First, we investigate whether these complex latent manifolds can be accurately described by a relatively small set of simple polynomial equations. The aim is to see if concise algebraic descriptions can capture the essential geometry of class-specific data representations within neural networks. Second, we explore how such polynomial characterizations, if obtainable, can be leveraged for class separation. The core idea is that even if data points from different classes are not yet linearly separable in a given latent space, their underlying manifold structures, once captured by these polynomials, might offer a direct path to distinguishing them. This is particularly interesting from an efficiency standpoint, as it suggests the possibility of replacing multiple complex, dense layers with more structured and potentially more compact polynomial computations, a concept we will explore through <em>vanishing ideals</em>.</p> <div class="figure-container"> <img src="/assets/img/blog_img/approximating-latent-manifolds-in-neural-networks/manifold_nn.png" alt="Manifold Neural Network" style="max-width: 80%;" class="zoomable" data-zoomable=""/> <div class="figure-caption">Neural networks transform input data manifolds. The output of a baseline NN (left) is often class probabilities. Our approach (right) considers the output of a truncated NN, where data from different classes may lie on distinct latent manifolds. We characterize these manifolds using polynomial equations derived from vanishing ideals.</div> </div> <h2 id="an-algebraic-view-on-latent-manifolds">An Algebraic View on Latent Manifolds</h2> <p>Recall that the latent manifolds we aim to characterize can often be described as <em>algebraic varieties</em>—the zero set of a system of polynomial equations. When we process data through a neural network up to a certain layer, the resulting activations (our points in latent space) can be viewed as a finite set of samples $\mathbf{Z} = \{\mathbf{z}_1, \dots, \mathbf{z}_m\}$ drawn from such an underlying manifold. From this set of samples, we can seek to find its algebraic description by computing the <em>vanishing ideal</em> $\mathcal{I}(\mathbf{Z})$, which is the set of all polynomials $p$ such that $p(\mathbf{z}_i) = 0$ for all $\mathbf{z}_i \in \mathbf{Z}$. These polynomials approximate the algebraic structure of the variety containing $\mathbf{Z}$, noting that a sample of the manifold is of course also only an approximation to the manifold itself.</p> <p>While $\mathcal{I}(\mathbf{Z})$ itself contains infinitely many polynomials, Hilbert’s Basis Theorem guarantees that it can be finitely generated. This means there exists a finite set of polynomials, known as <em>generators</em>, from which all other polynomials in the ideal can be derived through polynomial combinations and multiplications. The primary goal of vanishing ideal algorithms is to find such a set of generators, thereby providing a concise algebraic description of the data’s underlying structure.</p> <p>However, in practice, data from neural network latent spaces is often noisy, and we only have a finite number of samples. Attempting to find polynomials that vanish <em>perfectly</em> on these samples is typically impossible. Moreover, even if such polynomials were found, they would describe the specific sample set $\mathbf{Z}$ rather than generalizing to the underlying manifold $U$ from which $\mathbf{Z}$ was drawn. Therefore, instead of exact vanishing, we seek polynomials that <em>approximately vanish</em> on the data. That is, we look for polynomials $p$ such that $p(\mathbf{z}_i)^2 \leq \psi$ for all $\mathbf{z}_i \in \mathbf{Z}$, where $\psi &gt; 0$ is a small tolerance. Algorithms such as the Oracle Approximate Vanishing Ideal (OAVI) algorithm <d-cite key="wirth_conditional_2024,wirth_approximate_2023"></d-cite> or the Approximate Buchberger-Möller (ABM) algorithm <d-cite key="limbeck_computation_2014"></d-cite> are designed to find such approximate generators, building upon foundational work <d-cite key="livni_vanishing_2013"></d-cite><d-cite key="HELDT20091566"></d-cite> and offering a robust way to characterize manifolds from noisy, finite samples. Applying these algorithms to the high-dimensional, large-scale data found in neural network latent spaces presents its own set of computational challenges, which we address with specific strategies.</p> <p>Our first main goal is to characterize the structure of class-specific data manifolds as they are represented in the latent spaces of pre-trained neural networks. This involves applying vanishing ideal algorithms to the activation vectors produced by an intermediate layer of the network.</p> <p>However, applying these algorithms directly to the latent space data presents significant computational challenges:</p> <ol> <li><strong>High Dimensionality:</strong> Latent spaces, even in intermediate layers, can possess hundreds of dimensions. This poses a problem for standard vanishing ideal algorithms due to the combinatorial explosion in the number of potential monomial terms.</li> <li><strong>Large Sample Sizes:</strong> Neural networks are typically trained on huge datasets, leading to a large number of activation vectors that need to be processed by the vanishing ideal algorithms.</li> <li><strong>Generator Overload and Quality:</strong> Vanishing ideal algorithms can produce a huge number of generator polynomials. Many of these might be dense (involving many monomial terms) or lack the crucial property of being discriminative between different classes.</li> </ol> <p>To address these challenges, we employ the following techniques:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Stochastic Vanishing Ideal Computation:</strong> Instead of processing all data points for a class at once, we use stochastic variants of the algorithms. These operate on random subsets (mini-batches) of the latent activations, significantly reducing computational load and memory requirements.</li> <li><strong>Dimensionality Reduction:</strong> Before applying vanishing ideal algorithms, we use PCA on the latent activations.</li> <li><strong>Data Preprocessing for Numerical Stability:</strong> To improve the numerical stability of polynomial computations, latent activations are rescaled (e.g., via a Tanh transformation to map them into the $[-1,1]^n$ hypercube). We also explore using reduced arithmetic precision, which can further alleviate computational demands.</li> <li><strong>Selection of Discriminative and Sparse Generators through Pruning:</strong> Despite the aforementioned optimizations, the initial set of computed generators can still be very large, resulting in a large number of polynomials to evaluate during inference. We address this by removing (or pruning) polynomials that are not discriminative of the class. For each class, we evaluate its candidate polynomials. A polynomial is deemed valuable if it is <em>discriminative</em>—meaning it effectively vanishes (evaluates to near zero) on samples of its own class while remaining significantly non-zero on samples from other classes. Polynomials that don’t sufficiently meet this criterion are discarded. Alongside discriminative power, we prioritize <em>sparsity</em>: we favor polynomials with fewer monomial terms, as these are computationally more efficient to evaluate. Algorithms like ABM <d-cite key="limbeck_computation_2014"></d-cite> and OAVI <d-cite key="wirth_conditional_2024,wirth_approximate_2023"></d-cite> (especially when OAVI is used with the Frank-Wolfe algorithm) are good at producing such sparse polynomials. This dual-pruning strategy is essential: it not only selects for the most discriminative polynomials but also significantly reduces their total number and the complexity of their evaluation, leading to a compact and effective algebraic characterization of each class manifold.</li> </ul> <div class="figure-container"> <img src="/assets/img/blog_img/approximating-latent-manifolds-in-neural-networks/pruning.png" alt="Pruning of Polynomials" style="max-width: 90%;" class="zoomable" data-zoomable=""/> <div class="figure-caption">Illustration of our pruning process. Starting with a full set of monomials and generated polynomials (columns), we first prune polynomials with low discriminative scores (e.g., $p_2, p_4$). Due to the induced sparsity, many monomial rows may become all-zero (e.g., $x, xy, x^3$), indicating they no longer contribute to any remaining polynomial. These rows are also effectively removed, leading to a compact representation using only essential monomials (e.g., $y, x^2, y^2$).</div> </div> <h2 id="vi-net-replacing-network-layers-with-polynomial-expansions">VI-Net: Replacing Network Layers with Polynomial Expansions</h2> <p>Now that we have established methods for approximating the class-specific manifolds in a neural network’s latent space via their (approximate) vanishing ideal generators, we can make use of this algebraic insight. A primary goal is to enhance the efficiency of pre-trained neural networks. Deep networks, while powerful, often contain many computationally expensive layers. We propose replacing a significant portion of these final layers with a single, more structured <em>polynomial layer</em> built from the pruned generators discussed earlier.</p> <p>The fundamental concept is based on how these polynomial generators can achieve class separation. Even if data classes are not linearly separable in the chosen latent space of the truncated network, their distinct manifold structures, captured by the polynomial generators $\{p_i^k\}_{i=1}^{n_k}$ for each class $k$, can lead to <em>polynomial separability</em>. We achieve this by constructing a transformation $G$ as follows. For any latent vector $\mathbf{z}$ (the output of the truncated network), this transformation is defined as:</p> \[G(\mathbf{z}) = (|p_1^1(\mathbf{z})|, \dots, |p_{n_1}^1(\mathbf{z})|, \dots, |p_1^K(\mathbf{z})|, \dots, |p_{n_K}^K(\mathbf{z})|)\] <p>Here, $p_i^k$ is the $i$-th generator for class $k$, $K$ is the total number of classes, and $n_k$ is the number of generators for class $k$. The crucial property of this transformation is that if the input latent vector $\mathbf{z}$ belongs to a particular class $j$, its own generators $p_i^j(\mathbf{z})$ will evaluate to values very close to zero (as they <em>approximately vanish</em> on class $j$’s manifold). Conversely, the generators $p_i^l(\mathbf{z})$ for other classes $l \neq j$ will likely evaluate to significantly non-zero values. The output vector $G(\mathbf{z})$ thus has near-zero entries for the block of features corresponding to the true class $j$ and larger values for other blocks. This structure makes the transformed features linearly separable by a simple linear classifier. Our architecture that implements this approach is named <em>VI-Net</em>, and it represents our second main contribution.</p> <p>The VI-Net training pipeline is as follows:</p> <ol> <li><strong>Truncate Network:</strong> Start with a pre-trained neural network $\phi$ and truncate it at an intermediate layer $L’$.</li> <li><strong>Compute Vanishing Ideals:</strong> For each class $k$, extract the latent activations $\mathbf{Z}^k = \phi_{L’}(\mathbf{X}^k)$ and compute a set of approximate vanishing ideal generators using the adapted algorithms described above. Here, $\mathbf{X}^k$ is the set of samples from class $k$.</li> <li><strong>Prune Generators:</strong> Apply the pruning strategy to select the most discriminative and sparse polynomials for each class.</li> <li><strong>Construct Polynomial Layer:</strong> Use the selected and pruned generators $\{p_i^k\}_{i=1}^{n_k}$ for all classes to implement the transformation $G(\mathbf{z})$ as defined above.</li> <li><strong>Fine-tune:</strong> Append a simple linear classifier to the polynomial layer. Then, fine-tune the coefficients of the polynomials within the polynomial layer and the weights of the linear classifier using standard gradient descent.</li> </ol> <p>This approach offers several potential benefits, primarily from an <em>efficiency perspective</em>:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Parameter Reduction:</strong> The polynomial layer, especially after pruning, can have significantly fewer parameters than the multiple convolutional or fully connected layers it replaces. This leads to smaller model sizes.</li> <li><strong>Computational Speed-up:</strong> Evaluating a typically sparse polynomial layer can be faster than executing several dense layers, potentially increasing inference throughput.</li> </ul> <p>Our experiments demonstrate these benefits. For example, VI-Net variants built on ResNet architectures for CIFAR-10 and CIFAR-100 achieve classification accuracy comparable to the original, larger baseline networks, even when a substantial number of layers are replaced.</p> <div class="figure-container"> <img src="/assets/img/blog_img/approximating-latent-manifolds-in-neural-networks/cifar100.png" alt="Performance of VI-Net on CIFAR-100" style="max-width: 80%;" class="zoomable" data-zoomable=""/> <div class="figure-caption">Comparison on CIFAR-100 (ResNet-34) showing test accuracy versus the percentage of convolutional layers removed. Replacing layers with a simple linear head causes a sharp performance drop. VI-Net, using structured polynomials from vanishing ideals, maintains competitive accuracy far better than a layer of random monomials, demonstrating the importance of the algebraic structure discovered.</div> </div> <p>VI-Nets can be significantly more parameter-efficient and exhibit higher throughput, as shown in the table below.</p> <div class="table-container"> <table> <thead> <tr> <th colspan="6" class="table-header">CIFAR-10 (ResNet-18)</th> </tr> <tr> <th>Model</th> <th>Total Params</th> <th>Base Params</th> <th>Poly Params</th> <th>Acc (%)</th> <th>Throughput (img/s)</th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td>VI-Net18-Tiny</td> <td>1.86M</td> <td>0.68M</td> <td>1.18M</td> <td>88.62</td> <td>100798 ± 20506</td> </tr> <tr> <td>VI-Net18-Small</td> <td>2.84M</td> <td>2.18M</td> <td>0.66M</td> <td>92.66</td> <td>79307 ± 15576</td> </tr> <tr> <td>VI-Net18-Medium</td> <td>4.35M</td> <td>3.96M</td> <td>0.39M</td> <td>92.92</td> <td>71851 ± 13987</td> </tr> <tr> <td>VI-Net18-Large</td> <td>9.20M</td> <td>8.81M</td> <td>0.39M</td> <td>93.02</td> <td>62086 ± 11291</td> </tr> <tr class="border-top"> <td>ResNet18</td> <td>11.24M</td> <td>11.24M</td> <td>-</td> <td>92.89</td> <td>66533 ± 12577</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <div class="table-caption">Performance of VI-Net variants. "Total Params" (Millions) = "Base Params" (truncated ResNet) + "Poly Params" (polynomial layer). VI-Nets achieve comparable accuracy to baselines with fewer parameters and often higher throughput.</div> </div> <h2 id="conclusion-and-outlook">Conclusion and Outlook</h2> <p>This research creates a practical connection between manifold learning in neural networks and computational algebra. By adapting vanishing ideal algorithms, we effectively characterize the algebraic structure of class-specific manifolds within deep network latent spaces. The proposed VI-Net architecture demonstrates that these algebraic characterizations can construct polynomial layers to replace standard network components. This in turn yields models that are more parameter-efficient and can achieve faster inference while maintaining competitive accuracy.</p> <p>To reference this work in your research, please use the following citation:</p> <div class="language-bibtex highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="nc">@inproceedings</span><span class="p">{</span><span class="nl">pelleriti2025approximatinglatentmanifoldsneural</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="na">title</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="s">{Approximating Latent Manifolds in Neural Networks via Vanishing Ideals}</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="na">author</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="s">{Pelleriti, Nico and Zimmer, Max and Wirth, Elias and Pokutta, Sebastian}</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="na">booktitle</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="s">{Forty-second International Conference on Machine Learning}</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="na">year</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="s">{2025}</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="na">url</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="s">{https://openreview.net/forum?id=WYlerYGDPL}</span><span class="p">,</span>
<span class="p">}</span>
</code></pre></div></div>]]></content><author><name>Nico Pelleriti</name></author><category term="deep-learning"/><category term="algebraic-geometry"/><category term="manifold-learning"/><category term="computational-algebra"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Our ICML25 paper Approximating Latent Manifolds in Neural Networks via Vanishing Ideals introduces a novel approach to understanding data representation in neural networks through vanishing ideals. To characterize the structure of latent spaces, we scale vanishing ideal algorithms to handle high-dimensional data. The resulting algebraic characterizations can be used to replace standard network layers with more compact and efficient polynomial layers, leading to significant parameter reduction and potential improvements in inference speed while maintaining competitive performance.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Neural Discovery in Mathematics: Do Machines Dream of Colored Planes?</title><link href="https://maxzimmer.org/blog/2025/neural-discovery-in-mathematics-do-machines-dream-of-colored-planes/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Neural Discovery in Mathematics: Do Machines Dream of Colored Planes?"/><published>2025-05-29T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-05-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://maxzimmer.org/blog/2025/neural-discovery-in-mathematics-do-machines-dream-of-colored-planes</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://maxzimmer.org/blog/2025/neural-discovery-in-mathematics-do-machines-dream-of-colored-planes/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="the-chromatic-number-of-the-plane">The chromatic number of the plane</h2> <p>The Hadwiger-Nelson (HN) problem, first posed in 1950, asks a fundamental question at the intersection of geometry and combinatorics: What is the minimum number of colors needed to color the entire Euclidean plane $\mathbb{R}^2$ such that no two points at unit distance share the same color? This minimum number is referred to as the <em>chromatic number of the plane</em>, denoted $\chi(\mathbb{R}^2)$, as it is the chromatic number of the infinite graph with vertex set $\mathbb{R}^2$ and edges connecting pairs of points at unit distance. What makes this seemingly simple setup challenging is the combination between discrete choices (the colors) with continuous geometry (the distance on the plane).</p> <p>Despite over 70 years of research, the exact value of $\chi(\mathbb{R}^2)$ remains unknown. It is currently bounded between 5 and 7, i.e., $5 \le \chi(\mathbb{R}^2) \le 7$. Establishing lower bounds typically involves constructing finite <em>unit-distance graphs</em>—graphs with a high chromatic number, that is, graphs that can be embedded in the plane in a way such that edges connect points exactly one unit apart. Notable examples include the Moser spindle, which requires 4 colors <d-cite key="moser1961solution"></d-cite>, and a large graph discovered by Aubrey de Grey in 2018, proving $\chi(\mathbb{R}^2) \ge 5$ <d-cite key="DeGrey2018ChromaticNumber"></d-cite>. Conversely, upper bounds are demonstrated by providing explicit coloring patterns for the entire plane. The best-known upper bound of 7 is realized by many different constructions, the most well known of which is a coloring based on a hexagonal tiling of the plane <d-cite key="soifer2009mathematical"></d-cite>. Closing the gap between 5 and 7 remains a significant open problem in mathematics.</p> <p>In this work, we focus on improving the upper bounds. We explore how neural networks (NNs) can serve as a tool for mathematical discovery, guiding our intuition towards potential new constructions for this problem and its variants.</p> <h2 id="a-new-approach-neural-networks-for-mathematical-discovery">A New Approach: Neural Networks for Mathematical Discovery</h2> <h3 id="modeling-the-coloring-problem">Modeling the Coloring Problem</h3> <p>We introduce a new approach to generate colorings which avoid unit distance conflicts using NNs. The core idea is to reframe the combinatorial problem as a continuous optimization task that NNs are well-suited to handle. Instead of assigning a fixed color (a discrete choice) to each point, we relax the constraint by defining a probabilistic coloring. We train the NN to output a <em>probability distribution</em> over the available colors for any given point $(x, y) \in \mathbb{R}^2$.</p> <p>Let $p_\theta: \mathbb{R}^2 \to \Delta_c$ be an NN parameterized by $\theta$, where $c$ is the number of colors and $\Delta_c$ is the $c$-dimensional probability simplex. For an input point $x \in \mathbb{R}^2$, the output $p_\theta(x) = (p_1, …, p_c)$ represents the probability distribution over the colors that point $x$ can attain.</p> <p>We then train the network in an <em>unsupervised</em> way, that is, without labeled data. Instead, we define a way to measure how “bad” a probabilistic coloring is according to the problem’s constraints. The resulting loss function is differentiable thanks to the probabilistic nature of the relaxed problem, allowing us to measure the violation of the unit distance constraint within a finite region $[-R,R]^2$. For the standard Hadwiger-Nelson problem, the loss function calculates the <em>expected</em> probability that two points $x, y$ exactly one unit apart <em>do</em> share the same color when said colors are sampled from their respective distributions $p_\theta(x)$ and $p_\theta(y)$:</p> \[\mathcal{L}(\theta) = \int_{[-R, R]^2} \int_{\partial B_1(x)} p_\theta(x)^T p_\theta(y) \; \mathrm{d}y \; \mathrm{d}x,\] <p>where $\partial B_1(x)$ is the unit circle around $x$.</p> <p>In practice, we approximate this loss and its gradient using Monte Carlo sampling. At each training step, we sample a batch of $n$ center points $x_i \sim \mathcal{U}([-R, R]^2)$ and for each $x_i$, we sample $m$ points $y_{ij} \sim \mathcal{U}(\partial B_1(x_i))$ from the unit circle around it. The loss for the batch is then approximated by the average conflict probability:</p> \[\mathcal{L}(\theta) \approx \frac{1}{nm} \sum_{i=1}^{n} \sum_{j=1}^{m} p_\theta(x_i)^T p_\theta(y_{ij}).\] <p>The entire setup is differentiable with respect to the network parameters $\theta$, allowing us to use standard gradient descent algorithms (like Adam <d-cite key="kingma2014adam"></d-cite>) to iteratively adjust $\theta$ and minimize the loss. As the loss decreases, the network learns to assign probabilities such that points at unit distance are less likely to receive the same color.</p> <p>The following animation illustrates this learning process, showing how the initially random probabilistic coloring evolves over training iterations to form a structured pattern that minimizes conflicts. We depict $\text{argmax}\ p_\theta(x)$, i.e., for each pixel we choose the color which currently has the highest probability.</p> <div class="figure-container"> <img src="/assets/img/blog_img/neural_discovery_mathematics/training_evolution.gif" alt="Animation illustrating the NN's learning process" style="max-width: 100%;" class="zoomable" data-zoomable=""/> <div class="figure-caption">Animation illustrating the NN's learning process. Watch as the initially random probabilistic coloring evolves over training iterations, guided by the loss function, eventually forming a structured pattern that minimizes conflicts.</div> </div> <h3 id="guiding-mathematical-intuition">Guiding Mathematical Intuition</h3> <p>The NN acts as a powerful function approximator, capable of learning complex spatial patterns directly from the geometric constraints, largely without strong built-in assumptions about symmetry or periodicity. Crucially, we use this approach not to find fully automated proofs, but as a tool to guide mathematical intuition <d-cite key="davies2021advancing"></d-cite>. When the loss converges to near-zero, the resulting coloring often reveals highly structured patterns. While not clearly visible from the animation, the network mostly assigns very high probabilities to one color and near-zero probabilities for the others, except for the transitions between the regions. The patterns provide valuable insights that can inspire the development of formal mathematical constructions, which must then be rigorously analyzed and verified. The figure below shows an example of this process, comparing a probabilistic pattern discovered by the NN with the resulting formal construction derived from it.</p> <div class="figure-container"> <img src="/assets/img/blog_img/neural_discovery_mathematics/complete_nn_comparison_compact.jpeg" alt="NN output inspiring a formal 6-coloring" style="max-width: 100%;" class="zoomable" data-zoomable=""/> <div class="figure-caption">Left: A probabilistic coloring pattern suggested by the NN after training to minimize conflicts for a $(1,1,1,1,1,d)$ variant (defined later). Right: The formalized mathematical construction derived from the NN's output, published in a specialized venue <d-cite key="2024_SixcoloringsExpansion"></d-cite>. This coloring is valid for a specific range of $d$.</div> </div> <h2 id="coloring-variants-and-recent-progress">Coloring Variants and Recent Progress</h2> <p>While finding a 6-coloring for the original problem remains difficult (our NNs consistently find patterns needing seven colors, aligning with the possibility that $\chi(\mathbb{R}^2)=7$), this NN-based optimization approach proved highly successful on related variants of the problem.</p> <p>A key variant we studied is the $(1,1,1,1,1,d)$ coloring problem: coloring the plane with six colors s.t. pairs of points assigned the first five colors must avoid unit distance, while pairs assigned the sixth color must avoid a <em>different</em> distance $d &gt; 0$. Prior to our work, such colorings were only known to exist for $d \in [\sqrt{2}-1, 1/\sqrt{5}] \approx [0.414, 0.447]$ <d-cite key="hoffman1993almost"></d-cite> <d-cite key="soifer1994infinite"></d-cite>.</p> <p>To tackle this variant, we modify the loss calculation. Instead of penalizing only unit-distance conflicts for all colors, the loss sums the conflict probabilities for each color $k$ with its specific forbidden distance $d_k$. In the sampling approximation, for a batch of points $x_i$, we sample points $y_{ij}^{(k)}$ at distance $d_k$ from $x_i$ for each color $k$, and the loss becomes:</p> \[\mathcal{L}(\theta) \approx \frac{1}{nm} \sum_{i=1}^{n} \sum_{j=1}^{m} \sum_{k=1}^6 p_\theta(x_i)_k \cdot p_\theta(y_{ij}^{(k)})_k\] <p>where $d_1=…=d_5=1$ and $d_6=d$. This loss penalizes pairs $(x_i, y_{ij}^{(k)})$ having the same color $k$ if their distance is the forbidden distance $d_k$.</p> <p>We also explored other variants, such as the $(1,1,1,1,d_1,d_2)$ problem, where two colors have distinct forbidden distances $d_1$ and $d_2$. Our framework easily adapts by modifying the loss calculation to incorporate the specific distance constraints for each color pair. The figure below shows a heatmap of the minimum conflict rate found by the NN for the $(1,1,1,1,d_1,d_2)$ variant across different values of $d_1$ and $d_2$.</p> <div class="figure-container"> <img src="/assets/img/blog_img/neural_discovery_mathematics/heatmap_two_colors_free.png" alt="Heatmap showing minimum conflicts for (1,1,1,1,d1,d2) colorings" style="max-width: 100%;" class="zoomable" data-zoomable=""/> <div class="figure-caption">Minimum conflict rate (log scale) found by the NN for the $(1,1,1,1,d_1,d_2)$ variant across different values of $d_1$ and $d_2$. Darker blue indicates lower conflict, suggesting potentially valid colorings exist in those regions. The diagonal corresponds to the $(1,1,1,1,1,d)$ case.</div> </div> <p>Focusing on the $(1,1,1,1,1,d)$ variant, our NN approach, exploring different values of $d$, discovered patterns that guided us to formally construct and verify <strong>two new families of 6-colorings</strong>. These constructions were published in a specialized venue <d-cite key="2024_SixcoloringsExpansion"></d-cite> and are visualized below:</p> <div class="figure-container"> <div style="display: flex; flex-wrap: wrap; justify-content: space-around; align-items: flex-start; margin-bottom: 0.5em;"> <div style="flex: 1; min-width: 300px; margin: 0.5em;"> <img src="/assets/img/blog_img/neural_discovery_mathematics/firstcoloring_complete.jpeg" alt="First new 6-coloring pattern" style="width: 100%;" class="zoomable" data-zoomable=""/> </div> <div style="flex: 1; min-width: 300px; margin: 0.5em;"> <img src="/assets/img/blog_img/neural_discovery_mathematics/secondcoloring_complete.jpeg" alt="Second new 6-coloring pattern" style="width: 100%;" class="zoomable" data-zoomable=""/> </div> </div> <div class="figure-caption">Our two novel 6-coloring patterns. Pattern 1 (upper image) is valid for $d \in [0.354, 0.553]$. Red avoids distance $d$ (shown for $d=0.45$), others avoid distance 1. Pattern 2 (lower image) is valid for $d \in [0.418, 0.657]$. The dotted circles have unit distance radius, while the dashed circles have radius 0.657 and the dash-dotted circles have radius 0.418. <d-cite key="2024_SixcoloringsExpansion"></d-cite></div> </div> <p>Together, these NN-inspired constructions <strong>significantly expand the known continuum of realizable distances</strong> $d$ to $[0.354, 0.657]$, representing the first progress on this problem variant in 30 years.</p> <p>Note that the distance $d$ in the last color introduces an additional degree of freedom. While it would be possible to just run our approach for many values of $d$, we realized that we can parametrize whole families of colorings by including the distance $d$ in the input of the NN. Querying then network at $(x, d)$ then yields the probability distribution over the colors at point $x$ if the forbidden distance in the last color is $d$. To visualize the exploration process for the $(1,1,1,1,1,d)$ variant, the following animation shows how the probabilistic 6-coloring found by the NN (left) and its corresponding conflicts (right, where black points indicate violations) change as the forbidden distance $d$ for the sixth color varies:</p> <div class="figure-container"> <img src="/assets/img/blog_img/neural_discovery_mathematics/varying_d.gif" alt="Animation showing coloring and conflicts changing with distance d" style="max-width: 100%;" class="zoomable" data-zoomable=""/> <div class="figure-caption">Animation showing how the probabilistic 6-coloring (left) and its corresponding conflicts (right, black points indicate violations) change as the forbidden distance $d$ for the sixth color varies. Note that this visualization is produced by a single NN, which parametrizes a family of colorings.</div> </div> <p>The plot below further summarizes these findings by showing the minimum conflict rate achieved by the NNs across different distances $d$. Lower conflict rates suggest that a valid formal coloring might exist for that $d$. The blue region highlights the significantly expanded range of $d$ where our new constructions provide valid 6-colorings, compared to the previously known range shown in orange.</p> <div class="figure-container"> <img src="/assets/img/blog_img/neural_discovery_mathematics/distance_vs_conflicts.jpeg" alt="Conflict rate vs distance d for (1,1,1,1,1,d) colorings" style="max-width: 100%;" class="zoomable" data-zoomable=""/> <div class="figure-caption">Minimum conflict rate found by NNs across different distances $d$ for the $(1,1,1,1,1,d)$ variant. The orange region shows the previously known range of $d$ for valid 6-colorings, while the blue region shows the significantly expanded range enabled by our new NN-discovered constructions.</div> </div> <h2 id="almost-coloring-the-plane">Almost Coloring the Plane</h2> <p>Beyond the distance variant, our framework demonstrated its applicability to other related geometric coloring problems, such as “almost coloring” the plane, arising as a natural extension of the HN problem: what is the minimum fraction of the plane that must be removed such that the remaining points <em>can</em> be colored with $c$ colors without monochromatic unit-distance pairs? We introduced an additional $(c+1)$-th color, corresponding to the removed points, and used a Lagrangian relaxation approach. This involves a modified loss function that penalizes conflicts among the first $c$ colors while also penalizing the use of the $(c+1)$-th “uncolored” color via a Lagrange multiplier $\lambda$.</p> <p>Our numerical experiments for $c=6$ colors recovered patterns resembling known constructions involving intersecting pentagonal rods <d-cite key="pritikin1998all"></d-cite>. The table below summarizes our numerical findings for $c=1$ to $c=6$ colors, showing the approximate minimum density of points that must be removed. These results align well with the best known bounds <d-cite key="pritikin1998all"></d-cite> <d-cite key="parts2020percent"></d-cite>, further validating our approach.</p> <div class="table-container"> <table> <thead> <tr> <th># Colors ($c$)</th> <th>1</th> <th>2</th> <th>3</th> <th>4</th> <th>5</th> <th>6</th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <th>Best known density removed</th> <td>77.04%</td> <td>54.13%</td> <td>31.20%</td> <td>8.25%</td> <td>4.01%</td> <td>0.02%</td> </tr> <tr> <th>Our results (approx. density removed)</th> <td>77.07%</td> <td>54.21%</td> <td>31.34%</td> <td>8.29%</td> <td>3.60%</td> <td>0.03%</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <div class="table-caption"> Minimum density of points that must be removed ("uncolored") to allow a conflict-free coloring of the remaining plane with $c$ colors. Our numerical results align well with known bounds <d-cite key="pritikin1998all"></d-cite> <d-cite key="parts2020percent"></d-cite>. </div> </div> <h2 id="conclusion-and-outlook">Conclusion and Outlook</h2> <p>Our work highlights the potential of NNs as tools for mathematical exploration. By reformulating combinatorial geometry problems, like the Hadwiger-Nelson problem and its variants, as continuous optimization tasks, we can experimentally discover new and potentially interesting patterns. While these networks do not yield formal proofs directly, they effectively explore complex solution spaces and uncover structured patterns that can guide mathematical intuition.</p> <p>The discovery of two novel 6-colorings for the $(1,1,1,1,1,d)$ distance variant, significantly extending the known range of valid distances $d$ and marking the first progress in three decades, serves as a strong testament to this approach’s potential. It demonstrates how gradient-based optimization on continuous relaxations in combination with the powerful approximation capabilities of NNs can uncover combinatorial structures that have long eluded traditional methods, offering a promising new paradigm for tackling longstanding open problems in discrete mathematics and theoretical computer science.</p> <p>If you find this interesting and if this work is helpful for your research, please consider citing our paper:</p> <div class="language-bibtex highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="nc">@inproceedings</span><span class="p">{</span><span class="nl">mundinger2025neural</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="na">title</span><span class="p">=</span><span class="s">{Neural Discovery in Mathematics: Do Machines Dream of Colored Planes?}</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="na">author</span><span class="p">=</span><span class="s">{Mundinger, Konrad and Zimmer, Max and Kiem, Aldo and Spiegel, Christoph and Pokutta, Sebastian}</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="na">booktitle</span><span class="p">=</span><span class="s">{Forty-second International Conference on Machine Learning}</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="na">year</span><span class="p">=</span><span class="s">{2025}</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="na">url</span><span class="p">=</span><span class="s">{https://openreview.net/forum?id=7Tp9zjP9At}</span><span class="p">,</span>
<span class="p">}</span>
</code></pre></div></div>]]></content><author><name>Konrad Mundinger</name></author><category term="deep-learning"/><category term="ai4science"/><category term="ai4math"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Our ICML 2025 Oral Paper Neural Discovery in Mathematics: Do Machines Dream of Colored Planes? introduces a novel neural network approach to tackle the famous Hadwiger-Nelson problem and related geometric coloring challenges. We reformulate the combinatorial task as a continuous optimization problem, enabling neural networks to find probabilistic colorings. This led to discovering two new 6-colorings, marking the first progress in 30 years on a key variant involving different forbidden distances and significantly expanding the known solution range.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Capturing Temporal Dynamics in Tree Canopy Height</title><link href="https://maxzimmer.org/blog/2025/capturing-temporal-dynamics-in-tree-canopy-height/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Capturing Temporal Dynamics in Tree Canopy Height"/><published>2025-05-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-05-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://maxzimmer.org/blog/2025/capturing-temporal-dynamics-in-tree-canopy-height</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://maxzimmer.org/blog/2025/capturing-temporal-dynamics-in-tree-canopy-height/"><![CDATA[<div class="series-nav"> <div class="series-header"> <div class="title-row"> <span class="part-badge">Part 2 of 2</span> <h3>Series: Tree Canopy Height Estimation</h3> </div> <p>This post is part of a series of posts on tree canopy height estimation using deep learning and satellite data.</p> </div> <div class="posts"> <a href="/blog/2025/estimating-canopy-height-at-scale/" class="post inactive"> <div class="post-content"> <span class="post-title">Part 1. Global-Scale Forest Height Estimation</span> <span class="post-description">Introduction of the problem of estimating tree height from satellite data, its challenges and how we have overcome them in our ICML24 paper.</span> </div> </a> <div class="post"> <div class="post-content"> <strong class="post-title current">Part 2. Capturing Temporal Dynamics in Canopy Height</strong> <span class="post-description">Part 2 reveals how we moved beyond a single-year map to track changes in canopy height over time, as detailed in our ICML25 paper.</span> </div> </div> </div> </div> <h2 id="recap-learning-forest-height-at-scale">Recap: Learning Forest Height at Scale</h2> <p>This is the second part of the series on <em>Tree Canopy Height Estimation</em>. In <a href="/blog/2025/estimating-canopy-height-at-scale/">Part 1</a>, we discussed the motivation for using deep learning techniques on satellite data for forest height estimation and the challenges involved. We have seen how our method overcomes key technical challenges to generate accurate, high-resolution canopy height maps, resulting in a global forest height map for the year 2020. This post extends that work in an important new direction: we now track the canopy height over time.</p> <h2 id="what-are-we-missing">What Are We Missing?</h2> <p>While having a global forest height map might suggest that no more work is to be done, we are in fact missing out on a lot of information. In this post, we will explore some of the limitations of our current approach and discuss directions for improvements (and, non surprisingly, how we successfully address them). Two significant issues become apparent:</p> <h3 id="1-tall-trees-are-underpredicted">1. Tall trees are underpredicted.</h3> <p>Current models often struggle to accurately predict the height of tall trees. There’s a consistent underestimation that worsens as the trees get taller. This is a big issue because large trees store most of the carbon, making their accurate prediction crucial for climate analysis.</p> <h3 id="2-maps-only-capture-a-single-year">2. Maps only capture a single year.</h3> <p>Most maps, including our previous work, only capture a single moment in time. However, forests change due to disturbances, logging, and regrowth. Without tracking these changes, we miss the complete picture and can’t fully understand forest history or make informed predictions for the future.</p> <p>Before we discuss how we tackle these challenges, check out the figure below from our paper. It’s a short teaser of how much better we have gotten at predicting tall trees, comparing our latest work with the previous best and ALS data, which we aim to match.</p> <div class="figure-container"> <img src="/assets/img/blog_img/capturing-temporal-dynamics-in-tree-canopy-height/big_trees.jpeg" alt="Performance comparison on tall trees" style="max-width: 100%;" class="zoomable" data-zoomable=""/> <div class="figure-caption">Comparison of six canopy height maps with precise measurements obtained via aerial laser scanning (ALS). The patches contain tall trees exceeding 30 m in height. Our model is the only one that can accurately estimate the height of such trees.</div> </div> <h2 id="addressing-the-challenges">Addressing the Challenges</h2> <p>With these two problems in mind, we aimed to enhance the model from our previous work <d-cite key="paulsestimating"></d-cite>.</p> <p>Regarding the challenge of estimating tall trees, we identified a flaw in almost all existing models: they are trained on composite images, which are aggregations of all images captured over a year. In our previous work, we used the median of images taken at different times. This approach results in a loss of valuable information. We observed that Sentinel-2 images are not perfectly geolocated, and using images from different times allows the model to exploit these minor geolocation errors. Since the satellite does not fly over the exact same spot each time, each 10m pixel captures a slightly shifted reflection of the ground.</p> <p>As a solution, we change our model architecture to a 3D U-Net<d-cite key="cciccek20163d"></d-cite>, which is able to process a stack of monthly images. The monthly data is advantageous, as the model can see variations in structure and pixel reflectance values between seasons and also sees shadows for different sun angles. We modify the model to have a more efficient backbone, as we want to strike a balance between performance and compute needed for large-scale application.</p> <p>We further train not only on image and label for a single year, but from all images and labels from 2019 to 2022 (all years with full GEDI coverage). This way our model becomes invariant to different year-specific color variations and we can apply it to multiple years to get a temporal change map.</p> <h2 id="our-results">Our results</h2> <p>Since we do not preprocess our data to create composite images, the datasets we use are twelve times larger than in our previous work. In consequence, we limit our training and analysis to the European continent, comparing the following maps restricted to this region: Tolan et al. (2023) <d-cite key="tolan2023"></d-cite>, Liu et al. (2023) <d-cite key="liu2023"></d-cite>, Lang et al. (2022) <d-cite key="langGlobalCanopyHeight2022"></d-cite>, Turubanova et al. (2024) <d-cite key="turubanova_europe"></d-cite>, and our previous work Pauls et al. (2024) <d-cite key="paulsestimating"></d-cite>.</p> <div class="table-container"> <table> <thead> <tr> <th>Map</th> <th>Source</th> <th>MAE [m]</th> <th>MSE [m²]</th> <th>RMSE [m]</th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td>Tolan et al. (2023)</td> <td>Maxar</td> <td>11.25</td> <td>212.14</td> <td>13.25</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Liu et al. (2023)</td> <td>Planet</td> <td>8.17</td> <td>138.25</td> <td>10.36</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Lang et al. (2022)</td> <td>S2</td> <td>5.74</td> <td>84.68</td> <td>7.57</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Pauls et al.</td> <td>S1/2</td> <td>5.46</td> <td>83.14</td> <td>7.40</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Turubanova et al.</td> <td>Landsat</td> <td>12.39</td> <td>252.57</td> <td>14.14</td> </tr> <tr> <td><strong>Ours</strong></td> <td><strong>S1/2</strong></td> <td><strong>4.76</strong></td> <td><strong>74.28</strong></td> <td><strong>6.75</strong></td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <div class="table-caption">Despite the coarser 10 m resolution of Sentinel-1/2 (S1/2) compared to Planet (3 m) and Maxar (60 cm), our model yields highly accurate maps and achieves the best overall performance.</div> </div> <p>Our novel approach contributes in three key areas:</p> <h3 id="contribution-1-we-obtain-a-new-state-of-the-art-2020-height-map-for-europe">Contribution 1: We obtain a new state-of-the-art 2020 Height Map for Europe.</h3> <p>Our model outperforms all previous models in both quantitative and qualitative assessments. Compared to the second-best model, we achieve improvements of 13% in MAE, 11% in MSE, and 9% in RMSE. Additionally, our approach provides enhanced forest structure representation, more precisely aligned edges, and better differentiation between forest patches of varying heights.</p> <div class="figure-container"> <img src="/assets/img/blog_img/capturing-temporal-dynamics-in-tree-canopy-height/2020_comparison.jpeg" alt="Qualitative comparison of canopy height maps for the reference year 2020" style="max-width: 100%;" class="zoomable" data-zoomable=""/> <div class="figure-caption">Qualitative comparison of canopy height maps for the reference year 2020.</div> </div> <h3 id="contribution-2-we-obtain-significantly-better-results-for-tall-trees">Contribution 2: We obtain significantly better results for tall trees.</h3> <p>Our model predicts the height of large trees more accurately and is also able to detect single large trees close to larger areas of small trees, which has not been possible before. Further, our approach more closely matches the distribution of the labels and reduces the width of the scatterplot. This improves carbon stock estimates and helps spot old-growth forests.</p> <div class="figure-container"> <img src="/assets/img/blog_img/capturing-temporal-dynamics-in-tree-canopy-height/error_height_distribution.jpeg" alt="Canopy Height Error Distribution" style="max-width: 100%;" class="zoomable" data-zoomable=""/> <div class="figure-caption"> Boxplots for each model showing the 2020 mean error in every 5m bin between 10m and 40m. Although Liu et al. (2023), Pauls et al. (2024) and Lang et al. (2023) perform well on smaller trees, our models performs especially well for taller trees.</div> </div> <div class="figure-container"> <img src="/assets/img/blog_img/capturing-temporal-dynamics-in-tree-canopy-height/combined_scatter_histo_plots.jpeg" alt="Canopy HeightScatterplots and Histograms" style="max-width: 100%;" class="zoomable" data-zoomable=""/> <div class="figure-caption">Left: Scatterplots between 2020 GEDI labels and prediction for different models, including $R^2$ for all labels and $R^2_7$ for labels exceeding 7m. Right: Histograms of GEDI labels and all maps. Turubanova et al. and Tolan et al. saturate at 28 m, our model is the only one matching above 40 m.</div> </div> <h3 id="contribution-3-we-can-track-changes-over-time">Contribution 3: We can track changes over time.</h3> <p>By applying our model across multiple years (2019-2022), we can observe how forests evolve over time. Our approach successfully identifies disturbances and regrowth. However, a four-year span is insufficient to capture very slow growth due to high uncertainty levels.</p> <div class="figure-container"> <img src="/assets/img/blog_img/capturing-temporal-dynamics-in-tree-canopy-height/deforestation.jpeg" alt="TBD" style="max-width: 100%;" class="zoomable" data-zoomable=""/> <div class="figure-caption">Temporal maps illustrate the expansion of deforestation from 2019 to 2022. This is observed by comparing differences between each year, visible in both solitary forest patches surrounded by open land and within densely forested areas.</div> </div> <h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2> <p>Our approach to large-scale temporal forest height estimation surpasses all previous methods in accuracy, particularly for tall trees. Additionally, by applying our model across multiple years, we have developed a temporal change map capable of tracking disturbances and regrowth.</p> <p>A central limitation of our work is that, due to the huge dataset size, we only applied our model to the European continent. We plan to extend our work to the entire world in the future.</p> <p>To reference this work in your research, please use the following citation:</p> <div class="language-bibtex highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="nc">@inproceedings</span><span class="p">{</span><span class="nl">pauls2025capturing</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="na">title</span><span class="p">=</span><span class="s">{Capturing Temporal Dynamics in Large-Scale Canopy Tree Height Estimation}</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="na">author</span><span class="p">=</span><span class="s">{Pauls, Jan and Zimmer, Max and Turan, Berkant and Saatchi, Sassan and Ciais, Philippe and Pokutta, Sebastian and Gieseke, Fabian}</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="na">booktitle</span><span class="p">=</span><span class="s">{Forty-second International Conference on Machine Learning}</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="na">year</span><span class="p">=</span><span class="s">{2025}</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="na">url</span><span class="p">=</span><span class="s">{https://openreview.net/forum?id=ri1cs3vtXX}</span>
<span class="p">}</span>
</code></pre></div></div>]]></content><author><name>Jan Pauls</name></author><category term="deep-learning"/><category term="ai4science"/><category term="sustainability"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Our paper Capturing Temporal Dynamics in Large-Scale Canopy Tree Height Estimation was accepted to ICML 2025! In this work, we present a novel approach to generate large-scale, high-resolution canopy height maps over time. Using Sentinel-2 time series satellite data and GEDI LiDAR data as ground truth, we present the first 10m resolution temporal canopy height map of the European continent for the period 2019-2022. Our pipeline and the resulting temporal height map are publicly available, enabling comprehensive large-scale monitoring of forests.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Global-Scale Forest Height Estimation</title><link href="https://maxzimmer.org/blog/2025/estimating-canopy-height-at-scale/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Global-Scale Forest Height Estimation"/><published>2025-04-13T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-04-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://maxzimmer.org/blog/2025/estimating-canopy-height-at-scale</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://maxzimmer.org/blog/2025/estimating-canopy-height-at-scale/"><![CDATA[<div class="series-nav"> <div class="series-header"> <div class="title-row"> <span class="part-badge">Part 1 of 2</span> <h3>Series: Tree Canopy Height Estimation</h3> </div> <p>This post is part of a series of posts on tree canopy height estimation using deep learning and satellite data.</p> </div> <div class="posts"> <div class="post"> <div class="post-content"> <strong class="post-title current">Part 1. Global-Scale Forest Height Estimation</strong> <span class="post-description">Introduction of the problem of estimating tree height from satellite data, its challenges and how we have overcome them in our ICML24 paper.</span> </div> </div> <a href="/blog/2025/capturing-temporal-dynamics-in-tree-canopy-height/" class="post inactive"> <div class="post-content"> <span class="post-title">Part 2. Capturing Temporal Dynamics in Canopy Height</span> <span class="post-description">Part 2 reveals how we moved beyond a single-year map to track changes in canopy height over time, as detailed in our ICML25 paper.</span> </div> </a> </div> </div> <h2 id="intro-why-forest-monitoring-matters">Intro: Why Forest Monitoring Matters</h2> <p>Imagine having to measure every tree on Earth. It seems impossible, yet knowing the health and structure of our forests is a very important part of battling climate change. Forests not only act as a natural carbon sink, absorbing around half of the $CO_2$ from human activities, but they also provide habitat for countless species and are a crucial source of biodiversity. But how can we monitor these massive ecosystems that cover nearly one-third of the Earth’s land?</p> <div class="figure-container"> <img src="/assets/img/blog_img/estimating-canopy-height-at-scale/global_big.png" alt="Global canopy height map showing forest heights across the world" style="max-width: 100%;" class="zoomable" data-zoomable=""/> <div class="figure-caption">Our new global canopy height map shows forest heights across the world, with colors indicating tree heights from 0m (black/purple) to 35m+ (yellow).</div> </div> <p>Accurate forest height maps allow scientist to understand how much carbon our forests store and how it is distributed, to better identify and hence protect old-growth forests, as well as monitoring forest health and finally making informed decisions about forest conservation. Our new method provides more precise height estimates than previous maps, especially for short vegetation and complex forest areas. This enhances the ability of scientists and policymakers to understand and protect our forests resources.</p> <h2 id="the-challenge-of-global-forest-monitoring">The Challenge of Global Forest Monitoring</h2> <p>Traditional forest monitoring relies on field workers manually measuring individual trees. While this approach provides highly accurate data, it becomes impractical when trying to assess forests at a large scale. Furthermore, there’s a stark divide in monitoring capabilities: while industrialized nations have sufficient resources to conduct comprehensive forest surveys, many countries - particularly those home to crucial ecosystems like the Amazon rainforest and Congo Basin - lack the necessary resources to perform extensive monitoring of their forest landscapes.</p> <p>Satellite technology offers a solution. Modern satellites can regularly observe the entire Earth, offering a consistent way to monitor forests and general vegetation ecosystems worldwide. In particular, the GEDI mission, which is a full-waveform laser system on the International Space Station, can measure the height of every tree on the surface of the Earth. In practice however, the GEDI measurements are sparsely-distributed, taking up only a tiny fraction of the Earth’s total surface area. This is visible in the image below, where the GEDI measurements are shown in red/yellow dots.</p> <div class="figure-container"> <img src="/assets/img/blog_img/estimating-canopy-height-at-scale/Sentinel_GEDI.jpg" alt="Satellite imagery with height measurements" style="max-width: 100%;" class="zoomable" data-zoomable=""/> <div class="figure-caption">Satellite image overlaid with actual tree height measurements (red/yellow dots) from NASA's GEDI laser system. As the GEDI system is onboard the ISS, you can clearly see the ISS flight paths in the image.</div> </div> <p>The sparse distribution of GEDI measurements poses a challenge for creating a global map of forest heights. This is where deep learning, and in particular our research, comes into play. We introduce a new methodology to create a <strong>detailed, global-scale map of forest heights</strong> using supervised deep learning on satellite data. In particular, we combine:</p> <ul> <li>Radar images that can see through clouds (Sentinel-1) as input</li> <li>Optical images that show forest detail (Sentinel-2) as input</li> <li>Height measurements from NASA’s GEDI laser system as ground truth labels</li> </ul> <p>In other words, we train a model that takes satellite images as input and predicts the height of each pixel, training on the sparse GEDI measurements as ground truth labels. But learning heights from satellite images is not easy. Problems like clouds, mountains, and measurement angles make it challenging to get a good estimate of the height of the trees. We discuss our main challenges below:</p> <h3 id="challenge-1-dealing-with-clouds">Challenge 1: Dealing with Clouds</h3> <p>Satellites follow fixed orbits and capture images on a regular schedule, regardless of cloud cover. While most regions experience clear skies at some point during the year, allowing us to select cloud-free images, tropical regions pose a unique challenge. The persistent cloud cover and high-altitude cirrus clouds in these areas make it difficult to obtain clear optical satellite imagery, necessitating innovative approaches to extract useful data.</p> <h3 id="challenge-2-mountains-and-measurements">Challenge 2: Mountains and Measurements</h3> <div class="figure-container"> <img src="/assets/img/blog_img/estimating-canopy-height-at-scale/CanopyProblem.png" alt="The challenge of measuring trees on slopes" style="max-width: 100%;" class="zoomable" data-zoomable=""/> <div class="figure-caption">How slopes can trick our measurements: The same tree might appear taller when measured on a slope, and even in the absence of trees, GEDI records a height measurement.</div> </div> <p>Mountainous terrain poses unique measurement challenges. GEDI’s laser technology measures the height difference between the highest and lowest points within a 25-meter diameter circle. On steep slopes, this can distort measurements in two ways: trees may appear artificially taller than their true height, and even bare slopes register as having “height” due to the elevation change within the measurement circle.</p> <h3 id="challenge-3-location-accuracy">Challenge 3: Location Accuracy</h3> <div class="figure-container"> <img src="/assets/img/blog_img/estimating-canopy-height-at-scale/gedi_shift.png" alt="Shifted measurements example" style="max-width: 100%;" class="zoomable" data-zoomable=""/> <div class="figure-caption">Sometimes our measurements are slightly offset from their true location (each circle shows a height measurement).</div> </div> <p>Even with accurate height measurements, GPS and satellite positioning errors can cause misalignment between the reported and actual measurement locations. This spatial offset presents a critical challenge: How can we train a reliable model when our ground-truth training data may be shifted from its true position?</p> <h2 id="our-approach-to-forest-height-estimation">Our Approach to Forest Height Estimation</h2> <div class="figure-container"> <img src="/assets/img/blog_img/estimating-canopy-height-at-scale/pipeline.png" alt="Our processing pipeline" style="max-width: 100%;" class="zoomable" data-zoomable=""/> <div class="figure-caption">Overview of our approach: from satellite data to the global height map.</div> </div> <p>Our solution involves three main components, which we will explain below:</p> <p>(1) <strong>Multiple Types of Satellite Data</strong></p> <p>Our approach leverages two complementary satellite data sources from ESA: Sentinel-2’s high-resolution optical imagery (similar to Google Maps) and Sentinel-1’s radar data. The radar signals can penetrate clouds and even some vegetation layers, providing crucial data in areas where optical sensors are limited. We combine these inputs with height measurements from NASA’s GEDI laser system on the International Space Station, which serve as our ground truth labels.</p> <p>(2) <strong>Smart Cloud Handling</strong></p> <p>Although we use radar data, it is still beneficial to use optical data as often as possible, as it has a higher level of detail. We therefore try to construct a cloud-free image where possible. Sentinel-2 does not only capture a single image per year, but an image of the entire globe every 6 days. We therefore make use of all images and mask out clouds from every image. Lastly, we combine all images into a single image by taking the per-pixel median of all non-cloud pixel values. This step effectively removes almost all clouds from the image and reduced noise and inter-year-variability.</p> <p>(3) <strong>Model Training</strong></p> <p>We used a special loss function to address location erros in our ground-truth measurements. Our loss function allows the model to shift the measurements within a certain range if it is similar for all nearby measurements. Secondly, we pre-filter our labels to remove measurements that were taken on areas with a great slope.</p> <h3 id="results-comparing-to-existing-maps">Results: Comparing to existing maps</h3> <div class="figure-container"> <img src="/assets/img/blog_img/estimating-canopy-height-at-scale/global_and_regional_comparison.png" alt="Comparison of different approaches" style="max-width: 100%;" class="zoomable" data-zoomable=""/> <div class="figure-caption">Comparison of our map (second row) with previous global maps and a detailed regional map (our benchmark). Notice the improved detail in our results.</div> </div> <p>Visually, our new method shows significant improvements over existing global maps, successfully surpassing their accuracy and detail levels. Specifically, we achieve better detail in forest structure, more accurate height estimates, and clearer distinction between forest and non-forest areas. The visual quality of our results even closely approaches that of specialized regional maps.</p> <p>Let’s look at how well our method performs quantitatively. We compared our results with the two other existing global canopy height maps, namely the one from Lang et al. <d-cite key="langHighresolutionCanopyHeight2023"></d-cite> and the one from Potapov et al. <d-cite key="potapovMappingGlobalForest2021"></d-cite>, reporting metrics for all ground-truth measurements as well as only for ground-truth measurements with a height greater than 5m to emphasize the error on trees.</p> <div class="table-container"> <table> <thead> <tr> <th>Method</th> <th>Mean Absolute Error</th> <th>Root Mean Square Error</th> <th>Mean Absolute Error (for labels &gt; 5m)</th> <th>Root Mean Square Error (for labels &gt; 5m)</th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td>Lang et al.</td> <td>6.47m</td> <td>8.62m</td> <td>8.80m</td> <td>11.02m</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Potapov et al.</td> <td>6.92m</td> <td>9.25m</td> <td>10.01m</td> <td>12.43m</td> </tr> <tr> <td><strong>Our Method</strong></td> <td><strong>2.43m</strong></td> <td><strong>4.73m</strong></td> <td><strong>4.45m</strong></td> <td><strong>6.72m</strong></td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <div class="table-caption">Performance comparison of different canopy height estimation methods.</div> </div> <p><em>Our method achieves significantly lower errors across all metrics. For trees taller than 5m, we maintain this advantage with a mean absolute error of just 4.45m.</em> To better understand where our method performs well and where there’s still room for improvement, let’s look at the error distribution across different tree heights:</p> <div class="figure-container"> <img src="/assets/img/blog_img/estimating-canopy-height-at-scale/error_height_distribution.png" alt="Error distribution across tree heights" style="max-width: 100%;" class="zoomable" data-zoomable=""/> <div class="figure-caption">Error analysis across different height ranges. The boxes show the distribution of errors for each height range, with negative errors indicating underestimation. Notice how we (blue) maintain lower error rates and less variance, especially for trees up to 30m.</div> </div> <p>Looking at this analysis in detail, our method shows excellent performance for trees up to 20m in height, with strong accuracy continuing through the medium height ranges. However, we must acknowledge that very tall trees, particularly those above 30m, remain a significant challenge. This is especially pronounced in tropical forests, where canopy heights can exceed 40m - an important area we need to address in future work. Nevertheless, even with these challenges in tall tree estimation, our approach demonstrates notably lower error variance compared to previous methods across most height ranges.</p> <h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2> <p>Creating accurate global forest height maps is crucial for understanding and protecting our planet’s forests. Our method combines the latest satellite technology with machine learning to produce the most detailed and accurate global forest height map to date. While we’ve made significant progress, there’s still more to explore. Future improvements could include:</p> <ul> <li>Even better handling of mountainous regions</li> <li>More frequent updates to track changes over time</li> <li>Reducing the error for very tall trees</li> </ul> <p>Want to explore forest heights in your area? Our global canopy height map is available on Google Earth Engine. You can view our predicted forest height information for any location on Earth here: <a href="https://worldwidemap.projects.earthengine.app/view/canopy-height-2020">worldwidemap.projects.earthengine.app/view/canopy-height-2020</a>.</p> <p>If this work is helpful for your research, please consider citing our paper:</p> <div class="language-bibtex highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="nc">@inproceedings</span><span class="p">{</span><span class="nl">pauls2024estimating</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="na">title</span><span class="p">=</span><span class="s">{Estimating Canopy Height at Scale}</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="na">author</span><span class="p">=</span><span class="s">{Jan Pauls and Max Zimmer and Una M. Kelly and Martin Schwartz and Sassan Saatchi and Philippe Ciais and Sebastian Pokutta and Martin Brandt and Fabian Gieseke}</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="na">booktitle</span><span class="p">=</span><span class="s">{Forty-first International Conference on Machine Learning}</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="na">year</span><span class="p">=</span><span class="s">{2024}</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="na">url</span><span class="p">=</span><span class="s">{https://openreview.net/forum?id=ZzCY0fRver}</span>
<span class="p">}</span>
</code></pre></div></div>]]></content><author><name>Jan Pauls</name></author><category term="deep-learning"/><category term="ai4science"/><category term="sustainability"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Our paper Estimating Canopy Height at Scale was accepted to ICML 2024! In this work, we present a novel framework for global-scale forest height estimation. Using a deep learning approach that leverages large amounts of satellite data with only sparsely distributed ground-truth height measurements from NASA's GEDI mission, we achieve state-of-the-art accuracy with MAE/RMSE of 2.43m/4.73m overall, significantly outperforming existing approaches. The resulting height map facilitates ecological analyses at a global scale.]]></summary></entry></feed>